<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
  >
  <channel>
    <title xml:lang="en">Blog - mingard.io</title>
    <atom:link type="application/atom+xml" href="http://jekyllrb.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link>http://mingard.io/blog</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 03:55:36 GMT</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 03:55:36 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <description></description>
    <!-- <image>
      <description>Transform your plain text into static websites and blogs.</description>
      <url>http://jekyllrb.com/img/logo-rss.png</url>
      <title>Jekyll • Simple, blog-aware, static sites</title>
      <link>http://jekyllrb.com/</link>
      <width>144</width>
      <height>73</height>
    </image> -->
    
    <item>
      <title>Being Back</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2015/06/30/being-back</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After four months of being busy with study and work I’ve finally had time to sit
down and think about being back in New Zealand. To answer the obvious question
straight off: Yes, I want to return to Japan but no, I don’t have any definite
plans. Particularly since I’m a poor student and still have a year and a half of
my degree to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wellington may be small and expensive, but it&#39;s also wonderfully green ...&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Wellington may be small and expensive, but it&#39;s also wonderfully green ...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection-for-want-of-a-better-word-&quot;&gt;Reflection (for want of a better word)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did I learn last year? I won’t spend too long on this since it skates
dangerously close to canned clichés and pointless prattling, but I still think
it’ll be fun for me to look back at in 10 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japanese!&lt;/strong&gt; It’s the big obvious one … I’m flicking through my first-year
textbook now and wondering how it ever seemed hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independence.&lt;/strong&gt; It was my first time living alone, so I started maybe possibly
picking up the ghost of a few time management skills. Having said that, I’m
still at the stage of tossing up whether to do housework or homework for half
an hour, then getting annoyed because I could have finished one in the time it
took me to decide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking.&lt;/strong&gt; My skill level has improved tremendously since my first hesitant
experiments, and I’ve also become a lot faster — it’s great to be able to
whip something up in half an hour rather than spending hours just chopping
vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aikido.&lt;/strong&gt; I started it thinking I’d just do it for a year and then go back to
kung fu, but I ended up really enjoying it and wanting to continue. I’m
currently doing both martial arts at once and finding that although the
concepts complement each other, it’s all too easy to mix up similar moves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture.&lt;/strong&gt; I was rather put off the Japanese working culture (I’ll come back to
that) but it was awesome going to temples and shrines, uni events and tourist
spots. It was particularly fascinating to see the influence of Western culture
and how it’s being blended with traditional values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friendship.&lt;/strong&gt; My still-underwhelming social skills are much improved, partly
because I was forced to put myself out there and make friends, and partly
because I met so many amazing people. Plus, I now have friends all over the
world!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that list was longer than I expected. Time for another photo of Wellington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Much the same view, but showing that Wellington isn&#39;t just a small town in the hills - it&#39;s more or less a city&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Much the same view, but showing that Wellington isn&#39;t just a small town in the hills - it&#39;s more or less a city&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;japan-and-my-future&quot;&gt;Japan and my future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my biggest goal for last year was to decide whether Japan is somewhere
I’d like to spend my life, or just a cool place to visit. I’ve come away with
some idea of the working culture, and I’m not at all sure it would suit me.
I heard a lot about companies with one “no overtime day” per week, and the
anecdotal reason for Japan’s large number of public holidays is “people have to
be forced to take time off work”. The general idea seems to be that the more you
work, the higher you’ll be promoted — and even taking your statutory holiday
can damage your chances of promotion. I won’t say too much because I don’t really
know much and because, in all fairness, this culture is changing (partly due to the
new generation of Western-influenced people who consider the traditional working
culture restrictive and old-fashioned). Still, I don’t think I would do well in
an environment that intense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, I very much enjoyed living in Tokyo, so if I could find an
upstart software company with a more Western culture then I’d certainly be keen to
try working there. With this in mind, I’m thinking about applying to
teach Japanese in Japan for a year or two after uni — I’ve heard good
things about the JET programme, and I’d probably get a much better idea of
what the working lifestyle is like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Certainly quite grey and dreary-looking compared to Wellington, but exciting and charming in its own way&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Certainly quite grey and dreary-looking compared to Wellington, but exciting and charming in its own way&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;them-feels&quot;&gt;Them feels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say, I have strongly mixed feelings about being back (to the point
where I wondered about titling this post “Fifty Shades of Back” … although if
that book and movie are half as terrible as reviews make out, I don’t want that
association anywhere near here). I wish all my friends lived in the same place,
although having moved from Christchurch to Wellington for uni that’s nothing
new. I wish you could get Japanese ingredients more easily and cheaply in New
Zealand, and and vice versa while I was there. I wish Wellington had a more
convenient public transport system, but I wouldn’t want to sacrifice the city’s
green-ness and compact-ness for it. I’m happy to be back doing Computer Science,
but sad to have so few opportunities to speak Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, without being too melodramatic I do feel like this is the first time
I’ve actually made a home somewhere and then moved away (for some reason going off to uni doesn’t
count). Even after four months it’s quite a weird feeling, but given my love of
both countries (and desire to travel more widely) I suspect it’s only the first
of many times this will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I&#39;m sure this could symbolise something deep and meaningful, but I&#39;m not quite sure what ...&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I&#39;m sure this could symbolise something deep and meaningful, but I&#39;m not quite sure what ...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-other-news-&quot;&gt;In other news …&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve finally published my personal website! It’s pretty barebones at the moment,
but I plan to keep working on it. I also plan to keep blogging every once in a
while, although I’m not sure what I’ll actually write about. I guess I’ll throw
some stuff at the wall and see what sticks. So stay around … you may be surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I formally invite you to stay and see what happens&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I formally invite you to stay and see what happens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>North of the Wall</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2015/02/24/north-of-the-wall</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OK, so Hokkaido (the northernmost of Japan’s major islands) isn’t actually north of a wall. But it
does look surprisingly similar to some of the frozen landscapes of Game of Thrones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually got back to New Zealand a couple of weeks ago, so I should probably do a summing-up post
sometime soon. In the meantime though, I haven’t finished writing about my adventures before
leaving. I actually went to Hokkaido (with Jackie, of course) during my final week in Japan, mainly
to go and see the world-famous Snow Festival. It was certainly impressive … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The first sculpture we saw and arguably the coolest (I argue it was, Jackie argues it wasn’t). This was to celebrate the release of the new Star Wars movie later this year&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The first sculpture we saw and arguably the coolest (I argue it was, Jackie argues it wasn’t). This was to celebrate the release of the new Star Wars movie later this year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The sculptures are the main attraction — some are made of snow, others are made of ice&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The sculptures are the main attraction — some are made of snow, others are made of ice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;One of several ornate building sculptures&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of several ornate building sculptures&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;At one of the food stalls a guy was entertaining the crowd (particularly this boy) by whirling and waving a piece of batter in time to music&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;At one of the food stalls a guy was entertaining the crowd (particularly this boy) by whirling and waving a piece of batter in time to music&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A statue based on the anime “Evangelion” … which rocketed to the top of my want-to-watch list just based on the design of that robot&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A statue based on the anime “Evangelion” … which rocketed to the top of my want-to-watch list just based on the design of that robot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Even New Zealand has a sculpture!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Even New Zealand has a sculpture!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;In the evening many of the sculptures have spectacular light shows&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;In the evening many of the sculptures have spectacular light shows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The snowboarding competition was another highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The snowboarding competition was another highlight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It was also great to meet up with Julia, another exchange student, for Jingisukan (the Japanese name for what turned out to be New Zealand lamb!)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It was also great to meet up with Julia, another exchange student, for Jingisukan (the Japanese name for what turned out to be New Zealand lamb!)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end we spent the best part of two days (half our holiday) at the festival, but we did
discover some other interesting places as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We weren’t actually staying in Sapporo (the largest city and site of the snow festival) because by
the time I booked hotel rooms were hard to come by and incredibly expensive. The town we did stay in
was about an hour’s train ride away, and although it was small it did contain a rather fun science
center. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A demonstration of how a one-way mirror works provided an interesting photo opportunity&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A demonstration of how a one-way mirror works provided an interesting photo opportunity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Finally! Thanks to a clever optical illusion, Jackie is tall!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Finally! Thanks to a clever optical illusion, Jackie is tall!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The highlight, however, was this carefully restored space capsule&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The highlight, however, was this carefully restored space capsule&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also went on a trip to a chocolate factory. “Shiroi Koibito” is a famous Hokkaido souvenir, but
the company that makes this also does numerous other chocolate products and (rather like the Cadbury
factory in New Zealand) allows you to wander around their factory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;“Shiroi Koibito” means “white lovers” so of course there’s a place for you to get a photo taken with your significant other …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;“Shiroi Koibito” means “white lovers” so of course there’s a place for you to get a photo taken with your significant other …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The factory itself isn’t on the same scale as Cadbury’s New Zealand, but it’s still interesting to see&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The factory itself isn’t on the same scale as Cadbury’s New Zealand, but it’s still interesting to see&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;15.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;You can also view a collection of antique chocolate-related crockery&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;You can also view a collection of antique chocolate-related crockery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;16.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And the outside has beautiful illuminations at night&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And the outside has beautiful illuminations at night&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, another place I would highly recommend. I’d quite like to go back in summer (apparently
it’s not as hot as the rest of Japan) and go to a few other places around the island (it’s also
famous for hot springs and ice floes, neither of which we were able to see). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now — as I said at the start I’ll probably do a summary post at some point, but my
adventure in Japan is officially over. Time to start studying computer science again … and saving
money to go back! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Okinawa</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2015/01/30/okinawa</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought Okinawa, the group of islands out between Japan and Taiwan, was a natural paradise.
Unfortunately, the islands are so small and flat compared to the Japanese mainland that they have
essentially become sprawling towns (perhaps similar to Auckland) so although they have stunning
beaches, they can’t boast the same untouched beauty as parts of New Zealand. Having said that, going
on holiday there with Jackie made for a fun diversion from the overcrowdedness of Tokyo. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes about 3 hours to fly from Tokyo to Naha (the capital of Okinawa). It was dark by the time
we arrived so we didn’t get to see much, but we did see the sun setting prettily over the Pacific
ocean during the flight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Always hard taking photos from plane windows …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Always hard taking photos from plane windows …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended up having a very late start the first day — we woke up late and then spent a long time
faffing around trying to rent a car. We had quite a sober afternoon looking at war memorials,
particularly one dedicated to the Himeyuri girls, a group of over 200 students and teachers forced
to work as nurses during the American invasion of Okinawa in World War 2. These students were
eventually “discharged” from service when the success of the invasion seemed inevitable, and were
essentially thrown out of the caves they’d been working in to fend for themselves amid constant
bombardment from the American forces. Many jumped off cliffs and drowned, and many others committed
suicide. It was a real reminder that the moments everyone knows about (Hiroshima, Pearl Harbor, the
D Day landings) are only a tiny fraction of what happened during the war. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;One of the memorial stones outside the Hanayuri Memorial Museum&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of the memorial stones outside the Hanayuri Memorial Museum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We wandered around the Peace Memorial Park after dark, which was quite a spooky experience …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We wandered around the Peace Memorial Park after dark, which was quite a spooky experience …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day involved a much more cheerful visit to Okinawa World, a place which is very hard to
categorise. It’s basically a whole collection of souvenir shops with various attractions around
them, including a kilometre-long cave passage, traditional dance shows and a snake museum. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The caves are full of stalagmites and stalactites, all with names like “the Golden Cup” and “Lovers’ Plaza”.&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The caves are full of stalagmites and stalactites, all with names like “the Golden Cup” and “Lovers’ Plaza”.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My “I’m not sure what you’re trying to do but this is a photo so I’ll smile” face&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My “I’m not sure what you’re trying to do but this is a photo so I’ll smile” face&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Unfortunately we couldn’t take photos during the dance, but we were got one taken with a couple of the dancers afterward. For those interested, the dance style is called “Eisa”&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Unfortunately we couldn’t take photos during the dance, but we were got one taken with a couple of the dancers afterward. For those interested, the dance style is called “Eisa”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Holding a giant python at the snake museum — this was after a show featuring various snakes including a King Cobra. Note my thrilled face and Jackie’s slightly terrified one&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Holding a giant python at the snake museum — this was after a show featuring various snakes including a King Cobra. Note my thrilled face and Jackie’s slightly terrified one&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The park also had a tropical garden, so we got to try sugarcane and starfruit for the first time&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The park also had a tropical garden, so we got to try sugarcane and starfruit for the first time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our last full day we drove way up north to Okinawa’s most famous aquarium. Seeing whale sharks
was definitely the highlight of that outing, but unfortunately I couldn’t get any good pictures—the
sharks swim too fast for my poor phone and just look like grey smears in my photos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okinawa actually got its current name relatively recently — before that it was an semi-independent
kingdom with ties to China, known as Ryukyu. Before flying out, we managed to look around Shuri
castle, the home of the Ryukyuan kings of old. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A model of an official ceremony …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A model of an official ceremony …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;… and our attempt to recreate it&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;… and our attempt to recreate it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;These Chinese-style lions are everywhere in Okinawa&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;These Chinese-style lions are everywhere in Okinawa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Ryukyuan crown looks oddly like a ball of wool with a needle through it …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Ryukyuan crown looks oddly like a ball of wool with a needle through it …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more observations: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A surprising percentage of Okinawa’s land area is taken up by an American military base. This is
obviously a very controversial thing, but given the number of places which look like they cater to
off-duty American troops, Okinawa’s tourist industry would probably suffer if it was removed … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s a surprising amount of steak in Okinawa (it’s quite hard to find in Tokyo) — perhaps also
catering to the American appetite? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I definitely need to make a video game set here sometime — the culture is fascinating and the caves
and castles would look so cool! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, a fascinating trip. Okinawa is still definitely Oriental, but the culture, food and
atmosphere are surprisingly different from the Japanese mainland. Recommended! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo stories 5</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2015/01/29/photo-stories-5</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;hanayashiki&quot;&gt;Hanayashiki&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partway through the final term, Gakushuin’s clubs (or the Aikido club anyway) have some sort of
exchange with Konan University in Kobe. This year we played host, so the Konan students came to
Tokyo and, after a surprisingly small amount of shared training, we split up into year groups and
went off to show the Konan students the highlights of Tokyo. The “highlight” we first-years chose
was Japan’s oldest theme part, Hanayashiki. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hanayashiki is in Asakusa, so of course we got photos at the temple there as well …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hanayashiki is in Asakusa, so of course we got photos at the temple there as well …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hanayashiki doesn’t have a particular theme, but it’s nice to find a place which specialises purely in fun&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hanayashiki doesn’t have a particular theme, but it’s nice to find a place which specialises purely in fun&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;disneyland&quot;&gt;Disneyland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December I had a long-awaited visit from my family! Obviously it was great to see them, but this
also meant I went to a few places I hadn’t yet been. Chief among these: Disneyland! The actual
Disneyland, not DisneySea this time. I was curious how different it would be … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The answer: Much more Christmassy! Although there’s a slight chance that the time of year accounts for that&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The answer: Much more Christmassy! Although there’s a slight chance that the time of year accounts for that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;As before, I’m amazed at the sheer scale of the place&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;As before, I’m amazed at the sheer scale of the place&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Heaps of fun stuff, including a surprisingly good Star Wars ride (not shown here)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Heaps of fun stuff, including a surprisingly good Star Wars ride (not shown here)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wait times were also mostly reasonable, with only a few rides having the 2-hour-plus queues
Disneyland is infamous for. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;christmas&quot;&gt;Christmas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christmas in Japan is rather different to western countries. New Year is the time when families
traditionally get together, so Christmas is all about couples (it’s like a second Valentine’s Day).
Accordingly, I did some stuff with Jackie, as well as having a western-style Christmas party with
the rest of the exchange students. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Oh, and we had an Aikido Christmas party as well. Just decorating the club room beforehand …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Oh, and we had an Aikido Christmas party as well. Just decorating the club room beforehand …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jackie and I went to Shinjuku-gyoen, the big park I visited a hundred years ago in April. While
there wasn’t much in the way of autumn foliage left, we did manage take lots of photos in the
massive greenhouse. We also managed to get a turkey dinner (well, half of one; we didn’t book ahead)
at a very nice Irish pub downtown. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I was trying to take a funny photo showing that this leaf is about as long as Jackie is tall, but I got a cute one instead … ah well&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I was trying to take a funny photo showing that this leaf is about as long as Jackie is tall, but I got a cute one instead … ah well&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-year&quot;&gt;New Year&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting thing we did at New Year was going to Hatsu-mode, a traditional countdown event
held at temples and shrines across Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It was … fairly busy&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It was … fairly busy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’m surprised they were allowed to have this ceremonial brazier so close to the crowd …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’m surprised they were allowed to have this ceremonial brazier so close to the crowd …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I finally figured out what these are while my family was here — they’re barrels of sake donated to the temple. This company must have wanted a lot of blessings …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I finally figured out what these are while my family was here — they’re barrels of sake donated to the temple. This company must have wanted a lot of blessings …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it’s not traditional to send Christmas cards in Japan, New Years’ postcards are a massive
thing. It’s a tradition which goes back a long way, which of course means that the Aikido club makes
it of paramount importance. I ended up sending over 30, all of which had to be written out neatly by
hand. Needless to say, this took a very long time and used up all the days before Christmas when I
was hoping to write blog articles and so on. So I’m sorry about that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m posting two articles at once this time, so please continue on with me to Okinawa! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daigakusai</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/12/10/daigakusai</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Delayed as usual, this is the “interesting event” that I talked about in my last post. It’s a
tradition I was quite surprised by, although I’d be interested to know whether it exists in America
or any other Western countries … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about Gakushuin’s university festival: a time to eat food, watch performances and
generally see what university students are like in holiday mode. The festival took over the campus
on the first Saturday, Sunday and Monday of November, with Friday and Tuesday reserved for setting
up and packing down. This meant students without any festival activities to do got a five-day
holiday, but needless to say, I was not one of those people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university festival is a time for circles to set up stalls and sell food to raise funds for the
next year’s activities. It’s also a chance for bukatsu members to do more serious activities, while
looking condescendingly at the circle members and pointing out to each other how their club would
never stoop so low. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Aikido club’s serious activity was to hold an enbukai (martial arts demonstration) on the
Saturday. First-years don’t get to do anything particularly interesting, but it was still fun (and a
bit nerve-wracking) to perform some simple moves in front of our school’s shihan (grandmaster),
teachers, coaches and various past graduates. Clubs from other universities were also invited to
give demonstrations, so it was interesting to see their various styles. In the evening we had a
formal dinner with the teachers and older graduates followed by an informal party with the younger
graduates. Since the first and second-year students have to set up and pack up everything, we were
busy for most of the day (and some of Friday and Tuesday as well). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I managed to go and wander around the festival with Jackie on Sunday. Japanese “festivals”
all seem to follow one basic pattern: food stalls lining every path with people packed in between.
There’s also a standard set of festival food you can expect to find, including grilled
meat/chicken/squid, candyfloss, buttered potatoes, seaweed jelly and various cream-filled sweets. I
was expecting to find that set at the university festival as well, but I was pleasantly surprised by
some of the creative snacks on sale. Pancake-on-a-stick, anyone? Or perhaps you’d like fried bread
and ice cream? Or an Earl Grey tea scone? If you prefer something traditional, how about doing the
tea ceremony in a room decorated to look like a traditional village, with green tea and Japanese
sweets made by students? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I can’t remember why this guy was there, but he’s a samurai with Tokyo Tower on his armour and the Skytree on his helmet — he’d be awesome anywhere&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I can’t remember why this guy was there, but he’s a samurai with Tokyo Tower on his armour and the Skytree on his helmet — he’d be awesome anywhere&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the food, various clubs and circles do public performances. There seem to be an endless
number of dance circles from all sorts of genres at Gakushuin — you could spend almost the entire
three days going around and watching different dances. I didn’t. I watched two dance performances,
mainly because I had friends in both groups. One was a Japanese idol cover group: great dancers and
catchy songs, but the frilly outfits and cutesy attitude would make feminists cry! The other was
some sort of modern hip-hop thing (probably not actually, but I know virtually nothing about dance
styles), which was also fun. Naturally there were many other things we didn’t have time to see,
including comedy performances, plays and other martial arts demonstrations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I have no idea what the song was, but apparently in Japan it’s quite famous&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I have no idea what the song was, but apparently in Japan it’s quite famous&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually a shorter article than I expected; I guess the main message is “you had to be
there”. October and November are definitely the season for university festivals though, so I’d
definitely recommend going to a couple if you happen to be in Japan then. I enjoy the traditional
feel of religious festivals, but it’s equally fun to see something where people are simply showing
off and having a good time! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I really meant to take more photos during the daytime …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I really meant to take more photos during the daytime …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of weird lifestyle things this week, I’m going to introduce you to one infuriating aspect of
the Japanese language: Homophones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, Japanese has 5 vowel sounds which are used to make 52 basic syllables
(usually a consonant plus a vowel, such as ‘ka’, ‘te’ or ‘bo’). There are some compound sounds, but
it’s still a lot more limited than English with its vast array of inconsistent pronunciation. This
means that a lot of words end up being the same as each other. Sometimes there’s an almost
imperceptible difference in intonation (like Chinese) to let you know which word is meant, but there
are many cases where the intonation is the same as well. This means that in order to be sure which
word is being used, you need to see it written down in symbolic characters rather than just
phonetically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been several times recently when people have used words in conversation which I thought I
recognised but which seemed to make no sense in the context (or, worse, did seem to make sense,
meaning I completely misunderstood the sentence). Naturally I can’t think of any particular cases at
the moment, but I’ll give you a few examples of homophones which might cause confusion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kaki (かき; oyster) vs kaki (柿; persimmon) vs kaki (垣; fence) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tako (タコ; octopus) vs tako (凧; kite) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shifuku (私服; mufti/plain clothes) vs shifuku (至福; supreme bliss) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kougai (郊外; suburb) vs kougai (公害; pollution) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kagaku (科学; all sciences) vs kagaku (化学; chemistry) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m sure in the future I’ll laugh at how hard this seemed, but right now it’s quickly
becoming the most irritating part of Japanese. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, talking about pronunciation has made me think of an excellent poem I discovered today which
perfectly highlights how inconsistent and confusing English pronunciation is. The full text is
available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncf.idallen.com/english.html&quot;&gt;http://ncf.idallen.com/english.html&lt;/a&gt; but I’ve put a few of my favourite snippets below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now — I have two months left here so let’s see how much blog-worthy stuff I can do
before I leave! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lightning-fast update</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/11/23/lightning-fast-update</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, my courses have been going on for quite a few weeks now and my homework has been steadily
increasing, so this’ll be quite a short update on what I’ve been up to recently. Also, I have
something more interesting to tell of in an upcoming post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tokyo-tower&quot;&gt;Tokyo Tower&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The tower itself&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The tower itself&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally met up with one of my official buddies again to go to Tokyo Tower. This tower was
apparently built to look like the Eiffel Tower, except that for some reason it’s painted in stripes
of red and white. It’s roughly as tall as the Sky Tower in Auckland (for those who know New Zealand)
so although it’s nowhere near the tallest building in Tokyo you can still get some stunning views
from the top. Unfortunately it was cloudy that day, but you get the idea. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Weird when you’re 300m up and still can’t see the edge of the city in any direction&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Weird when you’re 300m up and still can’t see the edge of the city in any direction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also an aquarium and an amazing crêperie downstairs, along with the inevitable souvenir
shops and restaurants. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I love turtles anyway, but this has to be the coolest-looking one I’ve ever seen&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I love turtles anyway, but this has to be the coolest-looking one I’ve ever seen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-return-to-hiroshima&quot;&gt;The Return to Hiroshima&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last summer I worked for Catalyst New Zealand on a piece of software called Mahara. Later, I was
surprised to find out that there a large number of people who use Mahara in Japan, and that they
have an annual conference. After having this fact brought to my attention by Catalyst, I ended up
going to this year’s Mahara Open Forum in Hiroshima. I was pretty nervous, but thankfully the
attendees were both informal and welcoming, so I had fun trying to talk software development in a
mixture of Japanese and pidgin English. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I also got the chance to take a picture of the Atomic Bomb Dome in daylight&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I also got the chance to take a picture of the Atomic Bomb Dome in daylight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;russian-martial-arts&quot;&gt;Russian martial arts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to see a demonstration of Russian martial arts as part of some international relations stunt
is certainly one of the most unusual things I’ve done with the Aikido club. It was a great day out
though and fun to see some traditional Russian sports and costumes! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The man in fur is actually incredibly tall (even by my standards) so he spent most of the day striding through the Japanese crowd like some sort of demi-god&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The man in fur is actually incredibly tall (even by my standards) so he spent most of the day striding through the Japanese crowd like some sort of demi-god&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;People were encouraged to give everything a go during the afternoon — here the Aikido club captain is being thrown by one of the first-years in a “belt wrestling” match&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;People were encouraged to give everything a go during the afternoon — here the Aikido club captain is being thrown by one of the first-years in a “belt wrestling” match&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;yokohama&quot;&gt;Yokohama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s somewhere Jackie had been trying to take me for ages, but it was only a few weeks ago that we
finally made it to Yokohama. For those who don’t know, Yokohama is Tokyo’s port: Near the sea and
with plenty of interesting foreign influences. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And they say J. J. Abrams uses too many lens flares …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And they say J. J. Abrams uses too many lens flares …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;So one of the things they have in Yokohama is a massive Pokemon store …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;So one of the things they have in Yokohama is a massive Pokemon store …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And another is the Red Brick Warehouse (which is famous for some reason). Oh, and we happened to visit in the middle of Oktoberfest, so many sausages were eaten and much German beer was drunk&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And another is the Red Brick Warehouse (which is famous for some reason). Oh, and we happened to visit in the middle of Oktoberfest, so many sausages were eaten and much German beer was drunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yokohama is perhaps most famous for its massive Chinatown, home to hundreds of $20 all-you-can-eat restaurants!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yokohama is perhaps most famous for its massive Chinatown, home to hundreds of $20 all-you-can-eat restaurants!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;halloween&quot;&gt;Halloween&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently this is quite a big thing, at least in some parts of Tokyo. Unfortunately I had an Aikido
event the following morning so I couldn’t stay out as late as I would have liked, but it was still
fun being a dapper vampire (first chance I’ve had to wear my formal suit since arriving here) and
getting free drinks, free popcorn and free candyfloss in Shibuya. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yay for panicking about where to find vampire teeth 2 hours before the party, then giving up and using Kiwi ingenuity to make them out of an ice cream container, Sellotape and an orthodontic retainer&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yay for panicking about where to find vampire teeth 2 hours before the party, then giving up and using Kiwi ingenuity to make them out of an ice cream container, Sellotape and an orthodontic retainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a bar after the conference, I was introduced to the concept of “frozen beer”. Sadly it turned out
to be normal beer with frozen foam on top rather than an actual beer-flavoured snow cone, but it
was still a first for me &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escalators talk! Most don’t, admittedly, but the ones in the station I always use to get to work say
things like “This is an up escalator bound for exit 3” or “This is a down escalator bound for the
platform” when you step onto them &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo stories 4</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/10/07/photo-stories-4</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After my mixed experience in Kyoto, I was curious how the next part of my holiday would work out:
Spending a week travelling around Hiroshima (one of the best known places in Japan) and Shimane
(ranked bottom in tourist popularity last year) with my girlfriend Jackie. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started by visiting Miyajima, a small island near Hiroshima which contains a famous shrine,
various Buddhist temples and a lot of semi-wild deer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This massive torii (red gate, remember?) is the most famous place on the island&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This massive torii (red gate, remember?) is the most famous place on the island&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;When the tide is in, it covers all the ground you can see in this picture, making the shrine appear to be an island with the torii further out to sea&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;When the tide is in, it covers all the ground you can see in this picture, making the shrine appear to be an island with the torii further out to sea&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The island’s deer are totally comfortable around people, so much so that they will literally steal food out of your hands! Quite a shock when that first happened …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The island’s deer are totally comfortable around people, so much so that they will literally steal food out of your hands! Quite a shock when that first happened …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to Miyajima from Tokyo took most of the day, so we stayed the night on the island, planning
to do more exploring the next day. The island is mostly mountainous and uninhabited, so despite the
uninspiring weather it was nice to walk in real bush again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;There’s supposed to be an amazing view of Hiroshima through here …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;There’s supposed to be an amazing view of Hiroshima through here …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Not so different to New Zealand forest&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Not so different to New Zealand forest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various temples on top of the mountain, but apparently I don’t have photos of those. We
also tried oysters in batter (a local delicacy) and momiji-manjuu (snacks filled with flavoured
cream, which can be eaten raw, baked or deep-fried). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling we’d seen all that Miyajima had to offer, we headed back to the city for a sobering tour of
the Peace Museum. It’s a lot more graphic and shocking than I expected, and made the nuclear
disarmament stuff which a friend has been writing about over at Politics Personified seem a lot more
real and a lot more important. We then had a spooky night walk through the Peace Park to look at the
Atomic Bomb Dome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;In daylight the building looks a bit incongruous in the middle of a modern city, but it feels very different at night after going through the Peace Museum&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;In daylight the building looks a bit incongruous in the middle of a modern city, but it feels very different at night after going through the Peace Museum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We visited the statue of Sadako the next day, marvelling at how many organisations have donated paper cranes to put in the display cases around it&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We visited the statue of Sadako the next day, marvelling at how many organisations have donated paper cranes to put in the display cases around it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find that Hiroshima still has a military base and training camp when we visited
the adjoining museum. In a total contrast to the Peace Museum, it had all the standard things my
inner child can’t help but love— model boats, bits of torpedo, cool science stuff and more. That’s
not to say that it ignores the Pacific War, but it seems to give a rather different perspective on
it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Apparently big model ships with lots of guns are just as popular as peace memorials …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Apparently big model ships with lots of guns are just as popular as peace memorials …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was Hiroshima — city of peace and war. The next day we moved on to Shimane, a place I’d
never heard of until Jackie recommended it. The main attraction is yet another shrine, apparently
one of the oldest and largest in Japan, called Izumo-taisha. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;More symbolism I don’t recognise. Is that the sun on top of a wave perhaps?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;More symbolism I don’t recognise. Is that the sun on top of a wave perhaps?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The dark wooden construction is an interesting contrast to the bright red shrines in Kyoto&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The dark wooden construction is an interesting contrast to the bright red shrines in Kyoto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;There are various rabbit statues dotted around the shrine — these were particularly cute ones!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;There are various rabbit statues dotted around the shrine — these were particularly cute ones!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This massive symbolic knot shows that the shrine is dedicated to the Shinto god of marriage&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This massive symbolic knot shows that the shrine is dedicated to the Shinto god of marriage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we moved on to the capital of Shimane prefecture, a city called Matsue. There isn’t a huge
amount to do in Matsue, but that turned out to be a good thing since we both wanted some rest and
relaxation by this stage! However, we found time to wander (well … time for Jackie to wander and me
to be led) around various tourist attractions and historic sites. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This fearsome warrior welcomed us to Matsue castle — unfortunately I couldn’t understand much of his samurai Japanese …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This fearsome warrior welcomed us to Matsue castle — unfortunately I couldn’t understand much of his samurai Japanese …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The castle itself. Surprisingly, it’s the first castle I’ve been to since getting here that has the distinctive stepped shape I always associate with Japan&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The castle itself. Surprisingly, it’s the first castle I’ve been to since getting here that has the distinctive stepped shape I always associate with Japan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;15.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;All sorts of amazing suits of armour (and other historical artifacts) are displayed inside&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;All sorts of amazing suits of armour (and other historical artifacts) are displayed inside&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;16.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The view out over Matsue — small by Japanese standards but still quite big compared to most New Zealand cities!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The view out over Matsue — small by Japanese standards but still quite big compared to most New Zealand cities!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also visited the house of a famous author, who wrote (apparently) superb horror stories in
Japanese despite being Greek by birth. His name, for those interested, was Lafcardio Hearn, although
he’s better known by the Japanese name he assumed: Koizumi Yakumo. Unfortunately I didn’t take any
photos there … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on the day of our return to Tokyo, we traveled to a small town that’s one claim to fame is
that it’s home to a famous manga artist. Jackie is a big fan of the man’s most famous series (GeGeGe
no Kitaro), which centers around a supernatural boy who fights to protect humans from traditional
Japanese monsters. Seeing the vast array of creatures placed around the town (and hearing the theme
music over and over and over again through speakers placed all along the high street) did make me
want to read it as well, although I suspect I’d be more interested in learning about the monsters
than in the actual plot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;17.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;“Rat-man” — a friend of the protagonist and Jackie’s favourite character&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;“Rat-man” — a friend of the protagonist and Jackie’s favourite character&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;18.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Even the trains going to the town are themed with different characters from the series!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Even the trains going to the town are themed with different characters from the series!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, instead of weird things, this time I’ll give you the obligatory couple shot of us (taken at
a craft gallery in Matsue). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;19.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s most of the holiday stuff done. I’ll probably do another compilation to try and get up to the
present day (three weeks into term) but by then I guess a whole lot more things will have happened …
Anyway, thanks for reading! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aikido Summer Camp</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/09/26/aikido-summer-camp</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s traditional for Japanese clubs to have one or more camps during the year where all the club
members go away somewhere and spend a few days focusing on club activities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Aikido club this means going to Nagano prefecture (a 4-hour bus ride away from Tokyo),
staying in a ryokan (traditional inn) and training upwards of 6 hours a day for five days. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, a small diversion: While downloading camp photos from the club camera, I also came across
a whole lot of photos taken when we did Suica-wari earlier in the year. So here they are (finally). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Holding the sword the wrong way up was not a good start …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Holding the sword the wrong way up was not a good start …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;… but eventually I got the hang of it!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;… but eventually I got the hang of it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It wasn’t me that broke it, but yeah. That’s how badass we are.&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It wasn’t me that broke it, but yeah. That’s how badass we are.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Slightly bedraggled, but mostly triumphant&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Slightly bedraggled, but mostly triumphant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, fast forward a month or so to the camp itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We trained in a gym rather than a dojo, which meant real tatami rather than springy mats on the
floor. Tatami is surprisingly hard (well … hard compared to foam) so after 2000+ forward rolls we
were all quite scraped and bruised! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We had to take all the mats out of storage and lay them out ourselves — as well as being hard, tatami is surprisingly heavy!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We had to take all the mats out of storage and lay them out ourselves — as well as being hard, tatami is surprisingly heavy!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-days&quot;&gt;Training days&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days 2, 3, 5 and 6 all started with 6am training. This involved running up and down hills, with
occasional stops to do crunches and kubi-age (neck training). Already pretty exhausting, especially
when we hadn’t had breakfast yet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The food was worth waiting for though — since we were staying in a sort of Japanese inn it was both
tasty and plentiful. Apparently it’s a custom for senior club members to fill the rice bowls of the
juniors and the duty of the juniors to eat whatever is put in front of them. This meant we all got
either a lot of rice (from the kind seniors) or a vast amount of rice (from the other seniors)! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After breakfast was morning training — 45 minutes of fitness work (forward rolls, squats, ushiro-uke
backward breakfalls or tobi-uke flying breakfalls) followed by an hour and a bit of practicing
various techniques. We then had a short break before lunch (well, everyone else had a short break
while we first years set out lunch) followed by more training in the afternoon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After another short break it was dinner time. I should mention that before starting each meal we
were required to sit in seiza (Japanese-style kneeling, which is particularly hard on the knees and
calves) until told otherwise by the club captain. Usually we were allowed to stop kneeling and sit
comfortably during the meal, but during the third and fourth days (when we played host to
Endo-sensei, the chief instructor of our Aikido style) we had to stay in seiza for the entire meal.
Thankfully it’s the job of first years to get up occasionally and pour tea for the seniors, thus
giving our legs a little time to recover but it was still quite a sore experience! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dinner we usually had a meeting of some sort and then (once we’d finished our allocated
housekeeping tasks) it was time for bed. And another 5am wakeup call. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may get the impression that I didn’t enjoy this much, especially if you know how poor I am at
any sort of sustained physical activity. You would be right. However, I not only survived but
managed to finish all the training without any serious injuries, so I’ve definitely discovered that
my physical limits are a lot further than I thought! I know it’s nowhere near as hard as (for
example) an army boot camp, but to me it feels like a real achievement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This is yet another type of training —basically, the juniors are thrown by the seniors a set number of times (maybe a hundred, maybe more)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is yet another type of training —basically, the juniors are thrown by the seniors a set number of times (maybe a hundred, maybe more)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The final time we did that training, however, we were allowed to make the seniors do whatever we liked instead of the final throw. Some people did arm wrestling, dancing or thumb wars …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The final time we did that training, however, we were allowed to make the seniors do whatever we liked instead of the final throw. Some people did arm wrestling, dancing or thumb wars …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I decided to teach them some muscle exercises I find fun — some seniors were annoyingly good at them, but others were suitably shocked!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I decided to teach them some muscle exercises I find fun — some seniors were annoyingly good at them, but others were suitably shocked!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rest-day&quot;&gt;Rest day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, not every day was a training day. On the fourth day (the middle one) we had a sort of
rest day, which was actually great fun. We still had to get up at 5, but we did stretches instead of
training. We still had a morning training session with Endo-sensei, but instead of afternoon
training we visited hot springs. Sinking into an outdoor hot spring after two days of training has
to be one of the most relaxing experiences I’ve ever had. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Chatting and drinking milky coffee (apparently the traditional thing to have after visiting hot springs)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Chatting and drinking milky coffee (apparently the traditional thing to have after visiting hot springs)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;In the bus on the way back — no idea what I was concentrating so hard on, but it makes for a cool photo!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;In the bus on the way back — no idea what I was concentrating so hard on, but it makes for a cool photo!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We also bought souvenirs, and someone thought it would be a great idea to get a couple of foam swords. Half an hour later one was broken and someone had almost fallen down the stairs being chased with the other one&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We also bought souvenirs, and someone thought it would be a great idea to get a couple of foam swords. Half an hour later one was broken and someone had almost fallen down the stairs being chased with the other one&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s days like this when the barrier between seniors and juniors partially breaks down and everyone
becomes rather more equal, but the first year boys weren’t let off the hook entirely. We were
surprised by a “luggage check” in the evening during which the seniors ruthlessly searched through
our bags and “found” various (surprisingly explicit) items. With some of the quickest thinking I’ve
ever done in Japanese, I managed to explain that the reason an adult DVD was mysteriously discovered
in my luggage was that I wanted to improve my knowledge of Japanese culture. It might not sound like
much, but it’s probably the first genuine (and deliberate) joke I’ve made in a second language! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This translates to “Box for enjoying your night”. I don’t know what it contains, but I can hazard a guess …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This translates to “Box for enjoying your night”. I don’t know what it contains, but I can hazard a guess …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple more things happened that evening … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Firstly, the second year students turned the training hall into a haunted house completed with atomic bomb survivor, Japanese monsters, horror movie references and an alien&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Firstly, the second year students turned the training hall into a haunted house completed with atomic bomb survivor, Japanese monsters, horror movie references and an alien&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Secondly, each first year had to sing the school song, solo, from memory. This is me trying frantically to remember the words …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Secondly, each first year had to sing the school song, solo, from memory. This is me trying frantically to remember the words …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s strange how much your mind impacts your physical performance. I was shocked when we did forward
roll training twice in one day and could barely do any the second time, but the next time I knew
it was a possibility, mentally prepared, and ended up doing a whole lot better. Interesting for me
to discover such a radical example of mind over matter, especially since without thinking I wrote
that as my goal for the camp … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese guys rarely seem to smile in photos because “it looks cooler” to have a straight face. I
don’t agree. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Endo-sensei comes across as quite a friendly person (to me) but everyone else in the club seems
mortally afraid of him. Maybe it’s just because I’m a foreigner. Maybe his gentle corrections
sound a lot harsher if you understand the nuances of Japanese. But it still seems bad for learning
if everyone is too scared to ask questions &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo stories 3</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/09/12/photo-stories-3</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gakushuin’s summer holiday is drawing to a close, and I’ve been off travelling for quite a lot of
it. Kyoto isn’t the first place I went, but it’s the place it’ll be easiest to write about, so here
goes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went alone, which I like doing occasionally simply because it gives me a chance to take hundreds
of photos without worrying about inconveniencing anyone else, so when I said “write” before, I meant
“throw photos together with minimal captioning”. But I think that’s the best way for you to get a
feel for the place anyway. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a small diversion before we get to Kyoto: I ended up staying with my girlfriend and her parents
for a night before leaving, and happened to arrive on the day of their town’s summer festival. It
was surprisingly similar to the annual Santa Parade in New Zealand cities, with stalls lining the
streets, various buskers and other street performers, and an army parade. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This is … some sort of traditional dance&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is … some sort of traditional dance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Surprisingly, it’s cheaper to fly to Kyoto and back than to take the shinkansen&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Surprisingly, it’s cheaper to fly to Kyoto and back than to take the shinkansen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I planned to go and see a famous castle upon arrival, but by the time I found my hotel (time which
included getting lost twice …) it was close to closing time. Instead I went to Heian shrine — not
something I’d planned to do, but still an interesting first place to visit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Every shrine has a torii (red gate) some distance in front of it. This one is particularly large and impressive&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Every shrine has a torii (red gate) some distance in front of it. This one is particularly large and impressive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Flocks of these prayer-papers were tied to trees all over the shrine&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Flocks of these prayer-papers were tied to trees all over the shrine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The building itself is one of the most ornate examples of traditional architecture I’ve seen&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The building itself is one of the most ornate examples of traditional architecture I’ve seen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still feeling tired from the Aikido club camp (I’ll do an article about that as soon as I can
get photos off the club camera) so I went to bed early and planned for an early start. Unfortunately
I completely forgot to set an alarm, so I started considerably later than planned, but I at least
got up in time to see part of the morning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My first destination was Kiyomizudera, a famous Buddhist temple&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My first destination was Kiyomizudera, a famous Buddhist temple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;There are some idyllic spots inside, if you can find anywhere that isn’t full of tourists&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;There are some idyllic spots inside, if you can find anywhere that isn’t full of tourists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’d love to know what these statues represent— and why they have multicoloured bibs on&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’d love to know what these statues represent— and why they have multicoloured bibs on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This is just too many tourists for me to enjoy the place …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is just too many tourists for me to enjoy the place …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rather suspect I was put off by the crowds before seeing the best parts of the temple, but
Kiyomizudera didn’t live up to my expectations (which were admittedly very high after glowing
recommendations from several friends). I hoped the other places I planned to see were more
impressive and less busy, and thankfully I was right. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This is Fushimi-Inari shrine. Yes, it looks similar to other shrines, but it does have distinctive features …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is Fushimi-Inari shrine. Yes, it looks similar to other shrines, but it does have distinctive features …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The shrine is dedicated to a god who uses foxes as messengers, so there are many imposing statues of foxes holding scrolls and suchlike&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The shrine is dedicated to a god who uses foxes as messengers, so there are many imposing statues of foxes holding scrolls and suchlike&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The truly unique feature of this shrine is the line of 1000+ torii gates, which form a winding corridor around the hill beside&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The truly unique feature of this shrine is the line of 1000+ torii gates, which form a winding corridor around the hill beside&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Being inside the gates can be quite spooky …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Being inside the gates can be quite spooky …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;… but it allows for fun photos like this one!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;… but it allows for fun photos like this one!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling much happier, despite the continued crowds, I set off for what turned out to be my favourite
destination: Arashiyama. It’s a mountain on the outskirts of Kyoto which, in addition to more
shrines and temples, contains a monkey park and a bamboo forest, both of which I enjoyed immensely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;15.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The selling point of the monkey park is that the monkeys are wild — they wander around without cages or barriers.&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The selling point of the monkey park is that the monkeys are wild — they wander around without cages or barriers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are told to stay more than 3 metres away from the monkeys, but apparently no one told the
animals that — they’ll quite happily amble around and over your feet! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;16.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;You’re not allowed to feed the monkeys outside, but if you go into a specially designed hut you can feed them peanuts or apple pieces. They take the food with surprisingly delicate and human-like movements&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;You’re not allowed to feed the monkeys outside, but if you go into a specially designed hut you can feed them peanuts or apple pieces. They take the food with surprisingly delicate and human-like movements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;17.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;You can also get some pretty stunning views of Kyoto from the mountain&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;You can also get some pretty stunning views of Kyoto from the mountain&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;18.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s very hard to take photos of the bamboo forest, but it feels just like something out of “Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon” …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s very hard to take photos of the bamboo forest, but it feels just like something out of “Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon” …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the end of the second day; I’d planned to spend the third with a friend in Osaka but in the
end she wasn’t free, so I was able to spend an extra day exploring Kyoto (and explore at a leisurely
pace rather than the whirlwind tour I had planned). My first stop on the following day was the
castle that I had planned to visit on arrival: Nijoh-joh. It was built in 1626 as the Kyoto
residence of the Tokugawa shoguns, so it’s a bit like Windsor Castle in the UK (the “country house”
of the royal family). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;19.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Unfortunately you’re not allowed to take photos inside, but it really is a splendid place&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Unfortunately you’re not allowed to take photos inside, but it really is a splendid place&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particularly looking forward to walking on the nightingale floors that are one of the
distinguishing features of the castle, but unfortunately the sounds are quite hard to hear with
noisy tourists everywhere! I guess they would be much more effective on a silent and moonless night
as a ninja, dressed in dark blue (not black — ninjas never wore black) stalks toward the shogun … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also interesting seeing the different audience rooms, for the shogun to meet various classes
of people. These ranged from a small simple one (for minor nobles) to a large ornate one (for
important daimyo lords) to one decorated in reverse (for meeting the emperor or his messengers, the
only time the shogun wouldn’t be the most important person in the room). All the rooms had specially
designed screens and annexes to conceal the shogun’s bodyguards, and it was interesting to note that
the shogun would always be closer to his bodyguards than the people he was meeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also pleasantly surprised how much of the Japanese explanation I could puzzle out — although
kanji characters are hard to learn, you can figure out a lot of unknown words if you know the
meanings of the characters they’re made up of. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, since I still wasn’t tired of visiting temples, I visited Ginkakuji (the Silver Pavilion)
and Kinkakuji (the Golden Pavilion). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;20.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkakuji is famous for its beautiful Japanese garden. Which, for some reason, has a big pile of gravel as its centrepiece&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ginkakuji is famous for its beautiful Japanese garden. Which, for some reason, has a big pile of gravel as its centrepiece&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;21.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I love the wiggly trees you get in Japan&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I love the wiggly trees you get in Japan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;22.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kinkakuji, on the other hand, somehow looks like a toy; it doesn’t look possible that a building can be that, well, gold&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Kinkakuji, on the other hand, somehow looks like a toy; it doesn’t look possible that a building can be that, well, gold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that made for a busy few days, but I’m glad I went. The sheer number of tourists actually
made me a lot more determined to speak Japanese; I felt I had to show I wasn’t an ordinary foreign
visitor. I’d like to try visiting Nara next time though — I’ve heard it has a similarly large
collection of temples and suchlike but isn’t quite so tourist-filled. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find it surprising that despite visiting countless temples, shrines and other religious sites
during the holidays, no one ever tried to convert me or even tell me about Shinto or Buddhism.
Which, oddly enough, actually made me want to learn more about the monks’ beliefs &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese people buy an astonishing number and variety of charms and talismans compared to people in
Western countries—you can get premade charms for all sorts of things including exams, work, love,
pregnancy and general “domestic affairs” &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tokyo Disney Resort</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/08/22/tokyo-disney-resort</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You know how I talked about the horrible weather at the end of my last post? Well, there were a few
exceptions to that and (amazingly) one of them coincided with a weekday during term time when my
girlfriend and I were both free. So we went to Tokyo Disneyland. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should actually clarify that the place we went to was DisneySea rather than Disneyland. They’re in
the same place, but DisneySea has more exciting rollercoasters and is generally a more adult
experience. I wasn’t really expecting much (and winced at the entry fee) but the place totally
destroyed my preconceptions and turned out to be the best date I’ve ever had. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I was expecting something cheap and cheesy, with the rides and attractions designed to
draw your attention away from the surroundings, but I’m genuinely impressed how much effort was put
into the whole place. It really feels like stepping into another world. Oh, and I would have been a
lot more keen to go if anyone had told me that the theme is a cross between jazz-era America and
Victorian London with some steampunk and medieval stuff thrown in for good measure. You might think
that this made it a weird hodge-podge of styles and atmospheres but it’s all quite cohesive; it’s
surprising how natural it feels stepping straight from Aladdin’s palace into a Leonardo Da
Vinci-themed castle. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m rambling about something that’s very hard to describe in words, so I’ll let you get to the
photos now. Unfortunately I didn’t take very many, but they don’t do it justice anyway. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yay, sailing ships! Still one of my favourite things to look at, even when they’re obviously not historically accurate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yay, sailing ships! Still one of my favourite things to look at, even when they’re obviously not historically accurate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Part of Aladdin’s palace near a seller of excellent mango ice drink thingies&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Part of Aladdin’s palace near a seller of excellent mango ice drink thingies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;One half of the park, with the Tower of Terror standing out in the background&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One half of the park, with the Tower of Terror standing out in the background&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The other half of the park, mostly food places and stuff. There are actually some pretty nice-looking restaurants, not just the candy bars I expected&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The other half of the park, mostly food places and stuff. There are actually some pretty nice-looking restaurants, not just the candy bars I expected&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;So I realised after it got dark that I hadn’t taken any pictures of the volcano that’s the centrepiece of the park …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;So I realised after it got dark that I hadn’t taken any pictures of the volcano that’s the centrepiece of the park …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I wrap up, I’ll just mention two particular highlights (neither of which I have photos of).
We managed to go on the first day of Disney’s Summer Festival, which meant they put on various
performances including a jazz concert (my girlfriend and I have both played in jazz-ish bands so it
was a bit of nostalgia for both of us) and a spectacular lights show in the evening. The lights show
included boats, evil witches, flamethrowers and … well, do I need to go on? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have a feeling my memory may have exaggerated just how good the experience was but even
so, I can’t recommend this enough for anyone who comes here! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;fireworks&quot;&gt;Fireworks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post was going to be entirely about Disneyland, but I thought I’d stick this in as well. Japan
has a long history of letting off fireworks in summer at various events across the country — I don’t
know what the reason is (except that “it’s always been done”) but it’s great sitting back on a warm
evening with a drink of your choice and watching fireworks explode above the Tokyo skyline. The
fireworks are certainly larger and more numerous than any New Zealand show, but due to the crowds we
had to watch them from quite a long way away. It’s surprisingly annoying (for me) when the bang
comes several seconds after you see the firework explode … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japan doesn’t have summer and winter time like Western countries so you don’t have to bother about
changing the clocks every six months. However, this means that in summer it gets light before 5am
and dark before 7pm &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe not weird, but surprising to me: Tokyo Disneyland isn’t actually owned by Disney; all the
characters and locations are licensed by another company which owns all sorts of theme parks
around Southeast Asia &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to finish, something I keep wondering: How did people survive in places like this before air
conditioning? Or were there no humid 35° days until global warming took hold? &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, what’s been happening?</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/07/14/so-whats-been-happening</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s nearly the end of my first semester here. I’ve been a lot busier with study and Aikido
recently so I haven’t had time to do as much interesting stuff as before. So this is going to be a
catch-up post, a “best bits” reel of the past five weeks in preparation for the season finale,
Disneyland. Season 2 (otherwise known as the summer holidays) will start in a couple of weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;freshman-camp&quot;&gt;Freshman Camp&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year the first-year sports club members get together for a weekend of team building and pep
talking. This came as a relief to me, since I misunderstood the information we were given and was
expecting a weekend of hard training. Although, to be honest, a weekend of hard training would be a
lot more memorable than what actually happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stayed at a hotel in Yamanashi prefecture, which is a wonderfully picturesque part of Japan right
next to Mt Fuji. It’s a couple of hours’ bus journey from the university so (considering we left at
lunchtime on Saturday and returned early Sunday evening) we didn’t actually spend a lot of time
away. The hotel we were in was obviously pretty cheap, but it was still scrupulously clean with
ultra-respectful staff. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s nice that Japan still has places like this despite the “concrete jungle” nature of its cities&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s nice that Japan still has places like this despite the “concrete jungle” nature of its cities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really can’t say much about the activities, partly because there weren’t very many of them and
partly because I’ve forgotten a lot of it already. So much for this being an up-to-date journal … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one thing that stood out was a motivational talk by a guy who’s worked with many top
Japanese sportspeople and company executives. I remember it mainly because I understood about half
of what the man was saying, which I’m pretty pleased with. I certainly wouldn’t have known what he
was talking about at the start of the year. Aside from that there was a strange
performance/competition thing in the evening (which I didn’t understand at all), a video of sports
clubs from years gone by and a lot of speeches from various members of the school staff. All in all,
it was good to get to know the other Aikido first-years better, but it wasn’t the most amazing
experience I’ve had here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;suica-wari&quot;&gt;Suica-wari&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, on the other hand, is the sort of stereotypically Japanese thing that I thought couldn’t
possibly happen in real life. It literally means “watermelon splitting” and is something like
pinata, except that instead of hitting a paper animal you’re hitting a watermelon. And, since this
was an Aikido club event, instead of a stick we used a wooden sword. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently this is usually done at the beach, but we did it at uni after the final training session
of the term. The watermelon gets put on the ground (on a tarpaulin in our case) and people take it
in turns to be blindfolded and given the sword. The person is then spun around, after which everyone
starts shouting which way the watermelon is. It’s really confusing when twenty people are shouting
out different instructions in a foreign language (particularly since you have to be quite accurate
to actually hit the melon) but eventually you raise the sword up like a samurai and, in theory,
bring it slashing down onto the melon. In practice, the sword quite often smacks into the ground
just beside the melon, causing (in our case) many sore hands and one broken sword. I guess that’s
why it’s usually done on sand … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Unfortunately I didn’t take any photos and haven’t found many people who did, but this is the aftermath of a successful strike&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Unfortunately I didn’t take any photos and haven’t found many people who did, but this is the aftermath of a successful strike&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of using a wooden sword rather than just a stick is that it cuts the melon fairly
cleanly, meaning you can eat it afterwards without wasting any. And for anyone wondering, I managed
to hit (and shatter) my melon on my second attempt. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;asakusa&quot;&gt;Asakusa&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home to the most famous temple in Tokyo, this is definitely one of the coolest places I’ve been so
far. Which means I took a whole lot of photos. Which means I’ll show you those instead of just
writing about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kaminari-mon. It literally means “The Thundergate”, which just sounds like something from Lord of the Rings&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Kaminari-mon. It literally means “The Thundergate”, which just sounds like something from Lord of the Rings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Senso-ji is the most famous temple in Tokyo. It’s also one of the most crowded places I’ve been in, which is saying something&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Senso-ji is the most famous temple in Tokyo. It’s also one of the most crowded places I’ve been in, which is saying something&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The temple is so big that it’s really hard to take a good photo of it — this was from the top of a nearby building. Interesting contrast between the traditional temple and modern skyscraper&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The temple is so big that it’s really hard to take a good photo of it — this was from the top of a nearby building. Interesting contrast between the traditional temple and modern skyscraper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The interior is also spectacular&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The interior is also spectacular&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Asakusa is also home to a historic kimono museum, which is weirdly creepy when there’s no one else around. This scene, for example, is depicting a funeral procession&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Asakusa is also home to a historic kimono museum, which is weirdly creepy when there’s no one else around. This scene, for example, is depicting a funeral procession&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ueno-zoo&quot;&gt;Ueno Zoo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another place where I took a whole lot of photos. It’s pretty much like zoos everywhere, but I like
zoos everywhere so I enjoyed it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pandas are one of the main attractions. This has been rotated 90 degrees (the panda was actually sleeping) but I like the Kung Fu Panda effect&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Pandas are one of the main attractions. This has been rotated 90 degrees (the panda was actually sleeping) but I like the Kung Fu Panda effect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Trying to capture a polar bear with the “Motion Focus” mode I just discovered&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Trying to capture a polar bear with the “Motion Focus” mode I just discovered&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’m pretty sure these otters were trying to challenge the bear in the next enclosure&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’m pretty sure these otters were trying to challenge the bear in the next enclosure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;An obligingly photogenic tiger and a not-so-photogenic hand&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;An obligingly photogenic tiger and a not-so-photogenic hand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yeah, that’s pretty much how I feel on hot days&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yeah, that’s pretty much how I feel on hot days&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’m actually very impressed with this shot, considering that it was taken through glass with a phone&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’m actually very impressed with this shot, considering that it was taken through glass with a phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, a quick note about the weather. Japan’s rainy season (known as tsuyu) runs from the
middle of June to the middle of July and although it didn’t rain nearly as much as I expected (aside
from a few massive downpours) the weather has been horribly hot and humid for the past month or so.
It should be getting slightly less humid from now on, but it’s also likely to be even hotter, so I’m
incredibly thankful for the air conditioning in my room. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese people seem to go to temples and pray ritually without having much organised religion … I
imagine it would be fascinating for anyone doing a Religious Studies major &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people live several hours’ journey from where they work (I guess it’s more of a Tokyo thing
than a country-wide thing) so you see vast numbers of people sleeping on the trains. I thought
having to get up at 5am for Saturday training every week was bad, but having to do it every day
for work must be so much worse! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although Japanese food has a reputation for being healthy, they don’t seem to use many vegetables
(or much fish or meat for that matter — obento, the Japanese style of packed lunch, is usually a
large amount of rice with a small piece of fish and a few scraps of vegetable/seaweed on the
side). Unless their home cooking is drastically different from what they bring to school for
lunch, a high-carb, low-protein, low-veg diet must be better than many dieticians say … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aikido and a Taikai</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/06/09/aikido-and-a-taikai</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At New Zealand universities, clubs are pretty much something you join on a whim and occasionally
think about going to. At Japanese universities they play a much bigger role. However, before I get
started on this (probably lengthy) article I need to define the two sorts of clubs that you find
here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circle (saakuru) — Similar to a club in New Zealand, a circle is a group of people who meet up every
now and then to do something of mutual interest &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Club (bukatsu) — A far more serious organisation with multiple compulsory meetings per week &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which sort you join depends on your workload; if you join a bukatsu you’ll be expected to spend
about as much time doing club activities as you do studying. Since I’m not finding the workload here
too challenging, I decided to do so. Aikido sounded interesting and not too strenuous, so I decided
to give it a go. After four weeks of training, I’ve realised I was half right … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note, I also had a look at Kendo and Shorinji-kempo, as well as a few different circles.
There are an amazingly large number here compared to Victoria —as evidenced by the formidably large
book I was given at the start of the year which lists all the clubs and circles at the university.
Unfortunately it contains far too much complicated Japanese for me to actually read it so I
basically relied on word of mouth, but so far I’ve heard of clubs and circles for: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking (yeah, there are literally clubs where all you do is meet up once a week to get drunk) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music (both music appreciation and actually playing instruments) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traditional Japanese pastimes (calligraphy, flower arranging and so forth) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern Japanese pastimes (manga, card games, video games and suchlike) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sports (probably pretty similar to NZ — I’m staying well away) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martial arts (which were the ones that caught my eye — after doing Kung Fu for five years I’ve
developed a keen interest in martial arts) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aikido is turning out to be one of the strictest clubs, probably because one of the guiding
principles of Aikido is that it’s a way of life, not just a martial art. This means five 3-hour
training sessions per week, for which there is a massive amount of protocol to memorise. In addition
to “agtzmasu”, set phrases include “strshmasu” (“shitsurei shimasu”, an especially polite way of
saying “excuse me” or “sorry”) and “otsdshita” (“otsukaresama deshita”, said after training to
anyone who’ll listen as a way of saying “well done”). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I’ve never done Aikido before, I count as a first year, which means being polite to everyone
except other first years. Japanese is rather different when you’re talking politely — there are a
whole lot of grammar structures and verb forms you’re not allowed to use, plus a whole new set to
replace them. Thankfully, polite language was the first thing we learned in high school.
Unfortunately, it’s really hard to switch on-the-fly between it and casual language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s different again when an OB visits. OB is taken from the English “Old Boy”, but in
Japanese it’s a term of respect for a past graduate of the club. When talking to them we’re expected
to use ultra-polite and respectful keigo, which is yet another set of verb conjugations and grammar
patterns. Since I only started learning it last year, I’m pretty shaky on everything except basic
set phrases, but at least it’s a good opportunity to practice … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this might sound hard, everyone here is easy-going and forgiving of my mistakes. In fact, I
initially found the senior students’ cheerful disregard of my platitudes annoying, but over time
it’s become rather endearing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training itself is mostly fun, although it’ll take me a while to get used to the hour-long
muscle training sessions. Thankfully those don’t happen every class; the focus is very much on
“waza”, the same sort of set moves I’ve heard referred to as “kata” in Karate and “patterns” in Kung
Fu. For those who don’t know what Aikido is, here’s an example of what you can do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The idea is to redirect the energy of your attacker back at them rather than using your own strength&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The idea is to redirect the energy of your attacker back at them rather than using your own strength&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves feel very natural when you get them right, but there’s a lot to remember and a lot of
instincts and habits to unlearn. However, the fundamental concepts (such as balance, weight shift,
centre and circles) are very similar to Kung Fu so although I have a hard time remembering the
moves, I do generally understand how they work. There are about 30 people in the club so it’s great
being able to practice with various partners but annoying when everyone tells you different things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A taikai is an event where martial arts schools from all over the place come together to see what
the other schools are doing and to show off their own skills. There was an Aikido one in Tokyo a
couple of weeks ago, which we (the Aikido club) went to watch as a group. This was a big relief for
me since I had expected a grueling freshman camp that weekend. Much easier to get dates mixed up
when you only understand half of what people are saying … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s not a whole lot to say about it, except that it was far bigger than I expected and that some
of the demonstrations were very impressive. It’s amazing to watch a shihan (senior instructor)
apparently wandering aimlessly around a mat while attackers repeatedly bounce off him. Unfortunately
it didn’t include some of the multi-attacker drills I’ve seen on YouTube, but some of the
instructors came pretty close. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yeah … this is bigger than any martial arts venue I’ve seen before&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yeah … this is bigger than any martial arts venue I’ve seen before&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and New Zealand was represented as well (by more people than America, I was surprised and proud
to see). To be honest they seemed a bit sloppy compared to the over-disciplined Japanese, but their
moves looked just as effective. Obviously this is something to think about continuing when I get
back! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, because this is a longer post than usual, I’m going to make it even longer by including
(instead of my usual “weird things” section) a few things I miss from New Zealand and a few things I
will miss from Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things I miss &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steak (and other chunky meat) — meat here is usually thinly sliced, which is fine but no match for
an NZ stonegrill &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ease of communication— I’m at the stage where I’m tired of not understanding people and just want to
master Japanese already &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friends and family — it goes without saying, but I feel like saying it anyway. And I want to say
thank you to everyone who’s messaged/called me, including the people I haven’t had time to reply
to … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things I will miss &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vending machines — yeah, I know they exist in NZ, but there’s a difference between being able to buy
a bog-standard and overpriced range of Cola Cola drinks and being able to buy a vast range of
cheap and tasty iced tea, fizzy drinks and coffee &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rice balls and other cheap and filling snacks &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friends (again) — I thought it would be hard making friends here, but Japanese people are so
friendly and so delighted to see foreigners attempting to learn the language that it hasn’t been
hard at all &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I just mention that vending machine coffee again? I’m sure any students reading this will
appreciate the convenience of having hot or iced coffee available instantly for $1 a pop &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo stories 2</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/05/18/photo-stories-2</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Japan, public holidays are essential and numerous. Compared to New Zealand, it seems people take
their work way too seriously; although Japanese people are allowed to take paid holidays, people who
don’t tend to get promoted faster and get on better with their colleagues (who won’t have to take up
the slack while the person is away). Because of this, many people don’t take holidays at all unless
they’re actually mandatory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for many people Golden Week is the longest holiday they get all year — it’s formed by the
combination of four public holidays (April 29th and May 3-5th) and it is busy. I planned to go to a
whole lot of places (art galleries, museums, shrines) but I ended up giving up on that idea because
everywhere was just too crowded. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This was one of the times I found a clear space large enough to actually take a photo …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This was one of the times I found a clear space large enough to actually take a photo …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I managed to go to a few places, and also went on a trip to Hakone (a lake in the mountains
southwest of Tokyo) last weekend. I haven’t had the time or energy to write anything for the past
couple of weeks, and to be honest I don’t feel like writing much now either, so here’s my backlog of
photos from that period … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ueno: A place famous for museums and art galleries, but also for back streets (yokocho) which remind me of Hong Kong more than anything else&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ueno: A place famous for museums and art galleries, but also for back streets (yokocho) which remind me of Hong Kong more than anything else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yeah, apparently you can buy a whole octopus for about $10&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yeah, apparently you can buy a whole octopus for about $10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Bit of a sudden jump, but this is Tokyo Station a couple of days later&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Bit of a sudden jump, but this is Tokyo Station a couple of days later&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s impressive, but it looks rather out of place next to all the skyscrapers of central Tokyo&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s impressive, but it looks rather out of place next to all the skyscrapers of central Tokyo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The one time I needed people for a sense of scale, no one was there. Take my word for it, this is a forbiddingly wide path to the Imperial Palace&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The one time I needed people for a sense of scale, no one was there. Take my word for it, this is a forbiddingly wide path to the Imperial Palace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Before you get there, however, there’s a hotel with a rather fun watery bit outside. I believe this is what they call a “park” … seriously though, it’s a pretty cool mix of modernism and Zen principles&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Before you get there, however, there’s a hotel with a rather fun watery bit outside. I believe this is what they call a “park” … seriously though, it’s a pretty cool mix of modernism and Zen principles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I rather enjoyed the colours of the flowers — it made me realise there’s far too much grey here&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I rather enjoyed the colours of the flowers — it made me realise there’s far too much grey here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Annoyingly, this is about as much of the palace as you can see from the outside — or so I thought&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Annoyingly, this is about as much of the palace as you can see from the outside — or so I thought&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s weird seeing this much flat, empty space … apparently the palace isn’t a popular holiday destination, although the weather was a bitter final taste of winter&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s weird seeing this much flat, empty space … apparently the palace isn’t a popular holiday destination, although the weather was a bitter final taste of winter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yeah, sometimes I find bollards more interesting than palaces. Get over it&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yeah, sometimes I find bollards more interesting than palaces. Get over it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Now this is nice …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Now this is nice …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And this is nice as well. I would have loved to see inside the palace grounds, but it’s not a public place at all&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And this is nice as well. I would have loved to see inside the palace grounds, but it’s not a public place at all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;For the most part, Tokyo’s government buildings are supremely uninteresting. The Diet (Parliament) building is an exception&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;For the most part, Tokyo’s government buildings are supremely uninteresting. The Diet (Parliament) building is an exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;15.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And this is the national theatre. It seems a strangely uninteresting design for something that’s supposed to be a centre for the arts&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And this is the national theatre. It seems a strangely uninteresting design for something that’s supposed to be a centre for the arts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;16.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Supreme Court, on the other hand, is a fascinating piece of design. Unfortunately you can’t see it from any decent angles because the public isn’t allowed past the main gates&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Supreme Court, on the other hand, is a fascinating piece of design. Unfortunately you can’t see it from any decent angles because the public isn’t allowed past the main gates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;17.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Jumping again, this time to Hakone a week later. It really reminds me of some of New Zealand’s more beautiful places (Queenstown especially)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Jumping again, this time to Hakone a week later. It really reminds me of some of New Zealand’s more beautiful places (Queenstown especially)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;18.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Our ride arriving&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Our ride arriving&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;19.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;They alsohave a mock galleon that sails around the lake for some reason …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;They alsohave a mock galleon that sails around the lake for some reason …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;20.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;But … but where are the skyscrapers? The hordes of people? Why is there so much of that fluffy-looking green stuff everywhere?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;But … but where are the skyscrapers? The hordes of people? Why is there so much of that fluffy-looking green stuff everywhere?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;21.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A Tokugawa-era samurai villa, restored and made into a museum. This is the side of Japan I came to see&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A Tokugawa-era samurai villa, restored and made into a museum. This is the side of Japan I came to see&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;22.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photoshopping out that boat would make things look so much nicer …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Photoshopping out that boat would make things look so much nicer …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;23.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Oh, did I mention you can see Mt Fuji?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Oh, did I mention you can see Mt Fuji?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;24.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And did I mention how stunning it is?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And did I mention how stunning it is?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;25.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I still can’t believe this trip was free! Thanks Gakushuin!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I still can’t believe this trip was free! Thanks Gakushuin!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s about all for now. Apologies if this didn’t flow as well as my other posts, I’m tired out
from lack of sleep and constant Aikido training (which I’ll get to in my next article!) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just one final thing: If someone could tell me the name of this flower I’d be grateful! I’ve never
seen it before and it’s purty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;26.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things (note these are more subjective and theoretical than sometimes — this is just what I’ve
heard and inferred) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aside from what I said about work at the start of the article, I’ve heard a lot about how Japanese
companies expect to take students fresh out of university and keep them for 40+ years. This means
that if you want a good job, the university holidays are the last long holidays you’re likely to
get until retirement, and it puts massive pressure on fourth-year students to find a company
they’ll be happy with for their entire working life &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese companies tend not to worry about what sort of a degree you have as long as you have a
degree — they just expect to spend a few months training you when you arrive. In contrast to the
last item, I think this is an awesome idea: students can study what they are interested in without
worrying about whether it’ll make them employable &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tokyo is quite a small city given how many people are there. Driving across my home town of
Christchurch takes the best part of an hour, but driving across Tokyo only takes a couple of hours
even though it has 20-30 times the population &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orientation and classes</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/04/29/orientation-and-classes</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve now had over two weeks of classes so I figured it’s past time I let you know what I’m doing.
Orientation and lectures aren’t exactly the most interesting things that have happened here (which
is why I’ve put off writing about it for so long) but anyway, here goes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orientation was fun — most of the pictures I’ve posted of the university came from the tour my
buddies gave me. I have three buddies, all girls (apparently Japanese guys are too shy to apply …)
who have been incredibly helpful in doing all the administrative stuff that new residents+students
have to do. The main purpose of the orientation day was to meet them, but there was also a massive
amount of paperwork to be completed, with exciting titles like “Course Registration Form” and “New
Student’s Details Form”. I had to duplicate my name, date of birth and contact information on every
form, despite having provided them to the university in September last year. I handed back the last
piece of paper a few days ago, which is a big relief. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of classes, I’m focusing on Japanese (naturally) by taking three Japanese language courses
and one about grammar (for Japanese students, taught in Japanese). Aside from that, I’m taking a
German course and one on the history of war. The latter is taught in English so it’s nice and
easy — although I wasn’t planning to take anything like that, it proved too hard to find
Japanese-taught courses (aside from language ones) that I could actually understand. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if it’s the same at other universities in Japan, but the courses at Gakushuin seem to
involve a much lighter workload than those at New Zealand universities. Each course has only one
90-minute lecture per week and no tutorials, so unless we start getting a lot more homework in the
near future I shouldn’t have a particularly stressful year. In fact, I’ve found out that most people
are taking around 15 courses so it seems odd that I can take less than half as many and still get a
full year’s credit at Victoria … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Centre for International Exchange is a great place to hang out between lectures, for both exchange students and Japanese students&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Centre for International Exchange is a great place to hang out between lectures, for both exchange students and Japanese students&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s not much I can say about the teaching style, it seems to be the same at universities
everywhere. Whiteboard/projector/blackboard + teacher + students: the time-honoured formula which is
supposed to = learning. I am slightly disappointed by the lack of teaching technology (I was hoping
for sentient robots, but I have yet to see even a smartboard!) but it is interesting how precise and
ordered the teaching is here; I haven’t seen a teacher make a point using fewer than three colours
of pen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m the only person in two out of three of my Japanese classes — Gakushuin only has about 15
exchange students, and it turns out that most of them are better at the language than me. Still, I
certainly don’t mind having 3 hours of private tuition per week &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not exactly weird—and not really unexpected either — but almost all the white people are in the
intermediate class while the advanced class is mostly Korean and Chinese students. One day I’ll be
at that level … I hope! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apparently exams here are usually multiple-choice — to me that seems far too easy for a
university-level education, but I won’t argue &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one final thing (something which I think all universities should learn from): Gakushuin’s
buildings are clearly and intuitively named. And they all have obvious signs with that name. There’s
the Central building in the middle, then the building immediately north is called North 1 and north
of that is North 2. East of the centre is East 1 and, well, you get the idea. It’s made finding
classes a whole lot easier than it was at Victoria last year (no more trying desperately to figure
out what “VZ” stands for, then looking all over the map for the “Von Zedlitz” building …) &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo stories 1</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/04/22/photo-stories-1</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The macro shots in my previous post came from a day in Shinjuku Gyoen. My Japanese teacher
recommended it and as soon as I mentioned it to one of my new friends she organised a trip there. Or
maybe it was planned already since it turned out to be the birthday party of another (new) friend.
Either way, it’s definitely the most beautiful place I’ve been to so far. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Quite a few people here, but not as many as at Yoyogi Gyoen the previous week …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Quite a few people here, but not as many as at Yoyogi Gyoen the previous week …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And the park itself is rather more picturesque than Yoyogi&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And the park itself is rather more picturesque than Yoyogi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s so cool that there are places like this in the middle of one of the biggest cities in the world&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s so cool that there are places like this in the middle of one of the biggest cities in the world&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And especially weird to see this much open space&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And especially weird to see this much open space&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Not the greatest lighting, but that’s a picture postcard right there&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Not the greatest lighting, but that’s a picture postcard right there&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before, I’d been to a movie at Roppongi Hills, a fairly new district that includes art
galleries, shops, restaurants and the offices of various big companies (Google Japan, Konami,
Mitsubishi and more). The reason I spent an hour going there instead of ten minutes going to the
cinema in Ikebukuro was that I researched the logo and branding of Roppongi Hills a couple of years
ago for a design assignment. It was cool seeing the logo in context, and the buildings in Roppongi
(which were designed at the same time) are some of the coolest I’ve seen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I can’t get over how tall this is — especially since I was halfway up when I took this photo!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I can’t get over how tall this is — especially since I was halfway up when I took this photo!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then returned a couple of days ago to go to Roppongi Art Night, an annual event where there are
artworks and performances in the streets and in the buildings from sunset on Saturday to sunrise on
Sunday. Unfortunately I’d been to a party beforehand and missed most of the performances, but it was
still fun to wander around looking at the installations with a few of the other partygoers.
Incidentally, if you ever need character inspiration for a story, get yourself invited to a Latin
dance party in the back streets of Tokyo. I can guarantee you characters galore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Not an art installation as far as I know — just a random house near where the party was&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Not an art installation as far as I know — just a random house near where the party was&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hordes of people, as usual. More curtains were being made out of patchwork as we watched&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hordes of people, as usual. More curtains were being made out of patchwork as we watched&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’m not sure what was going on in here, but it was obviously fascinating…&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’m not sure what was going on in here, but it was obviously fascinating…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Of course you can’t have an art show without product placement&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Of course you can’t have an art show without product placement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Apparently hundreds of lit-up whiskey bottles constitutes art these days. It did look pretty darn cool though&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Apparently hundreds of lit-up whiskey bottles constitutes art these days. It did look pretty darn cool though&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;You could feed handfuls of “winking leaves” (leaf-shaped cards with an open eye on one side and a closed one on the other) into the chimney and watch them burst out the top&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;You could feed handfuls of “winking leaves” (leaf-shaped cards with an open eye on one side and a closed one on the other) into the chimney and watch them burst out the top&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day I looked around Gokokuji (the area surrounding a famous temple) with one of the same
friends. It contains things like another beautiful garden, the largest cathedral in Tokyo and a
random house with cool flowerpots outside, but I’ll let the pictures speak for themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;13.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A random house with cool flowerpots outside&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A random house with cool flowerpots outside&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;14.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The largest cathedral in Tokyo — so large that it’s impossible to photograph the whole thing&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The largest cathedral in Tokyo — so large that it’s impossible to photograph the whole thing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;15.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hey, it’s me looking slightly stretched by the fisheye lens&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hey, it’s me looking slightly stretched by the fisheye lens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;16.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Every chapel should have this feeling of tranquility&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Every chapel should have this feeling of tranquility&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;17.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;And every cathedral should have this majesty. This one is a little dark for my taste though —it almost looks to me like they’ve set up a church in the middle of the Death Star&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And every cathedral should have this majesty. This one is a little dark for my taste though —it almost looks to me like they’ve set up a church in the middle of the Death Star&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;18.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A lovely overgrown, Japanese-style garden&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A lovely overgrown, Japanese-style garden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;19.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Apparently a single golden carp costs 1,000,000 yen ($10,000)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Apparently a single golden carp costs 1,000,000 yen ($10,000)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;20.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I wanted to play around with my camera settings to try and get a good shot from behind the waterfall, but there wasn’t really time …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I wanted to play around with my camera settings to try and get a good shot from behind the waterfall, but there wasn’t really time …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, to cap off this ridiculously long and photo-filled post, I’ll leave you with one final
photo: Tokyo by night, from the 60th floor of the Sunshine Center in Ikebukuro. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;21.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuzzy, but you get the idea. And the idea is “wow”&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Fuzzy, but you get the idea. And the idea is “wow”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things (only one this time, but it’s one I’ve noticed a lot) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese people will whip out umbrellas at the slightest hint of a drizzle and stare at me weirdly
if I don’t do the same. This is actually one instance where I don’t mind being stared at since it
saves me the trouble of a) remembering to bring an umbrella, b) bothering to get it out and c)
remembering and bothering to dry it when I get home &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;22.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s … not actually raining&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s … not actually raining&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanami shiyou!</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/04/13/hanami-shiyou</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is an ancient and honourable Japanese tradition to drink sake while sitting under blossoming
cherry trees. This is known as hanami and it’s a fun and relaxing way to spend an afternoon. I was
lucky enough to arrive in cherry blossom season, and a Japanese friend I met over summer was kind
enough to invite me to a hanami last Saturday. This, then, is the story of that afternoon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hanami’d in a place called Yoyogi Park, near Harajuku. It’s part of a larger green area which
surrounds Meiji Jingu, a famous shrine. I didn’t know the shrine was nearby or I would have insisted
we visited it, but I imagine I’ll be able to go some other time. The park itself is an interesting
fusion of Japanese and English styles; winding paths through cherry blossom are interspersed with
Western-style flowerbeds and hedges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It took us a while to find somewhere we could sit down …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It took us a while to find somewhere we could sit down …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also a very busy place, especially on a Saturday afternoon at the end of the cherry blossom
season. We had to walk quite a way to find a patch of ground that wasn’t covered with a tarpaulin,
along a path packed with people doing much the same thing. I plan to go back at an off-peak time
just to see what the park looks like without crowds streaming through it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;No grass grows on this ground … but someone kindly lent us a tarpaulin&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;No grass grows on this ground … but someone kindly lent us a tarpaulin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we had found a spot someone pointed out that we had no food and only a six-pack of beer.
Someone else pointed out that there are no convenience stores or supermarkets near the park, so it
took a couple of hours for people to go and buy food. I, meanwhile, had something else to occupy me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised (although perhaps I shouldn’t have been) to find a couple of other foreigners in the
party, one of whom had been in my Japanese class the previous year. Of course it turned out that my
friend had known one of them in New Zealand and they were both on exchange at Tokyo University of
Foreign Studies. It was a relief to converse in English for a while, although I might have been
happier speaking exclusively Japanese. I want to practice as much as I can before the inevitable
culture shock kicks in. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At last the culinary expedition returned and I was introduced to a variety of Japanese snack foods,
including sushi made from some sort of fermented beans (bad-smelling but surprisingly tasty), cold
dumpling-like things in a sweet sauce and various dried potato snacks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Most people had packed up and left by this stage, but there were still more than there ever are in most New Zealand parks …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Most people had packed up and left by this stage, but there were still more than there ever are in most New Zealand parks …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went home at dusk, but not before kicking a ball around for a while and meeting a couple of other
groups of people including foreign tourists from various places. Taking foreigners to a hanami seems
like a popular thing to do, and with good reason — it’s a distinctly Japanese experience that’s
relaxing and enjoyable, and even if you don’t like it you can just keep drinking until you do! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are very few rubbish bins around Japan. This is apparently because it makes people more likely
to take their rubbish home and reuse/recycle it, but it does lead to massive piles of rubbish
around the bins that do exist &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I was moving the camera around too much to get a good picture, but it gives you an idea …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I was moving the camera around too much to get a good picture, but it gives you an idea …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese phones are not just locked to the carrier they’re bought with, the SIM card is locked to
the particular phone you buy it with. They’re “registered” as a pair, which is why you can’t just
buy a SIM card for a foreign phone. There’s probably more to this system than it appears, but it
seems to counteract the whole point of SIM cards … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the following photos were actually taken today at a more informal gathering at Shinjuku
Gyoen National Garden, but they do give you an idea of the types of tree you find in Japanese parks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;What people don’t notice about cherry trees is that the leaves are quite pretty too&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;What people don’t notice about cherry trees is that the leaves are quite pretty too&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This looks like a natural bouquet&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This looks like a natural bouquet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;These trees are so cool, they provide a nice counterpoint to the dominant green of spring&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;These trees are so cool, they provide a nice counterpoint to the dominant green of spring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University lectures have now started, so I’ll let you know how my classes go. I also have many more
beauty shots of Shinjuku Gyoen, the university and other random places in Tokyo so stay tuned! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An end to the “A ___ of ___ and ___” posts</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/04/10/where-i-live</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I said last week I’d write more about where I’m living so I’m sorry it’s taken so long. I also
received complaints from certain pedantic people that there were no pictures of flowerbeds in my
last post, so I’ve given up on the “A &lt;strong&gt; of &lt;/strong&gt; and __” titles for now since they would just have
become even more contrived. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had my first day of classes (posts about the orientation and lectures and stuff will come
shortly) so I’ll also give you a quick photo tour of the university. This is also the start of the
barrage of macro photography which is likely to come throughout the year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Cherry blossom! Also a hint about a future post …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cherry blossom! Also a hint about a future post …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the place I live. It’s a dormitory/apartment type place where exchange students from many
different universities live. It’s called Azalea House, or azeria-hausu in Japanese. Yes, they have a
word for “azalea” and one for “house” but they still prefer to Japanise the English words. I can
only assume it sounds cooler to a Japanese person. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having talked to some of the other people here, it sounds like I’m lucky to have a 40-minute commute
to university. In fact, having talked to some of the people at university, it sounds like a
90-minute commute is quite normal here. That’s probably not surprising to some people but to me
(given that I’ve never lived more than 15 minutes away from school or university) it sounds
terrible! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Azalea House. It has vending machines and a bike rack outside as a matter of course; everyone cycles here and you’re never more than a 2-minute walk away from a vending machine&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Azalea House. It has vending machines and a bike rack outside as a matter of course; everyone cycles here and you’re never more than a 2-minute walk away from a vending machine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from my window. Couldn’t have asked for better, really&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The view from my window. Couldn’t have asked for better, really&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This is Heiwadai (the surrounding suburb). More built up than most New Zealand suburbs, but still surprisingly, well, suburban for Tokyo&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is Heiwadai (the surrounding suburb). More built up than most New Zealand suburbs, but still surprisingly, well, suburban for Tokyo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Having said that, the city is never far away&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Having said that, the city is never far away&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Tokyo strikes me as a rather beautiful city in a slightly haphazard, let’s-build-everything-we-can-think-of-and-see-if-it-works kind of way&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Tokyo strikes me as a rather beautiful city in a slightly haphazard, let’s-build-everything-we-can-think-of-and-see-if-it-works kind of way&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the university is about 40 minutes away, most of which is walking — the train only
takes 10 minutes to get most of the way, but it’s a 15-minute walk at either end. I was a little
worried about how much it would cost to commute (the trains aren’t really cost-effective for short
distances), but I now have a special student card which lets me travel to and from university for
free. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university itself is an interesting place. Pictures will be easier than words so I’ll shut up
(figuratively speaking) and let you read the captions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;One of many impressive entranceways. There are usually guards in fancy uniforms and white gloves, but apparently not when this was taken …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of many impressive entranceways. There are usually guards in fancy uniforms and white gloves, but apparently not when this was taken …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;There’s cherry blossom everywhere on campus&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;There’s cherry blossom everywhere on campus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I’m not sure what this building is used for, but it’s pretty!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I’m not sure what this building is used for, but it’s pretty!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The architecture here is fascinating — most buildings have arched windows and a slightly medieval style on the lowest floor and a “normal” modernist style for all the other floors&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The architecture here is fascinating — most buildings have arched windows and a slightly medieval style on the lowest floor and a “normal” modernist style for all the other floors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Heaps of new students in suits for the opening ceremony yesterday&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Heaps of new students in suits for the opening ceremony yesterday&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;12.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;More cherry blossom … at least I think it is&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;More cherry blossom … at least I think it is&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s about all I have time for now, but more posts about my recent exploits are on the way. There
are reasons why I haven’t posted anything for the past week! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traffic lights are horizontal here, but the pedestrian stop/go signs are vertical. It’s probably
copied from somewhere, but to my perfectionist eye it makes no sense — could they not just pick an
orientation and stick with it? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My phone doesn’t work here so it’s strange not being constantly online. I even have to arrange to
meet people at certain times in advance and assume they’ll make it on time rather than texting
when I’m on the way! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Japanese, “thank you” is “arigatou gozaimasu.” As you might imagine, that’s too long for most
people to bother saying. However, it’s rarely shortened to “arigatou” (as I was led to believe in
Japanese class) since that’s too casual for most situations — apparently mushing it into
“agtzmasu” is a more appropriate thing to do &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to close, a random Japanese word I learned today: shoten means “book shop”. The reason I’m
mentioning this is that I used to use honya (which has the same meaning) but found out today that it
makes me sound like a primary school student. According to my teacher I should be moving on to
junior high school level Japanese, so from now on I shall use shoten. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A city of lights and flowerbeds</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/04/03/lights-and-flowerbeds</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to start by explaining a couple of things I glossed over in my previous post. Firstly, when
I said Aiko ended up showing me around Tokyo, I actually meant Akihabara, the district I’ve wanted
to go ever since hearing about it in Year 9 Japanese. It’s a place geared specifically towards anime
and manga (comic and animation) nerds so it contains some of the coolest and strangest places in
Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Akihabara is a place of towering skyscrapers, massive billboards and screens, seething crowds of
people and all the other clichés that I would expect from Tokyo. I was therefore surprised how
within five minutes of arriving, Aiko pulled me into a small, neat, traditional-looking sushi bar. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you hadn’t realised, I’m not talking about the sushi you find in New Zealand, where
everything is either salmon or chicken and the rice tastes like it’s been sitting in that box for
the past week. I’m talking about real sushi, countless varieties made to order by a knife-wielding
chef. It’s annoying when you spend ten minutes trying to puzzle out a few of the items on a vast
menu while listening to everyone else shouting out their orders without even glancing at it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m exaggerating of course, but I’m glad Aiko was there to recommend things. I’m still not sure what
I ate, but it was delicious! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Perhaps unsurprisingly, we passed an anime convention a few blocks after leaving the train station&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, we passed an anime convention a few blocks after leaving the train station&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the meal, we wandered around for a while before I happened to mention that I’d heard about
meido-cafe (maid cafés) in class last year. Aiko assumed from this that my greatest desire would be
to go to one, so we went to one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kawaii!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Kawaii!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who haven’t heard of them, a meido-cafe is a café where all the waitresses are dressed up
in cute and over-the-top maid outfits, mince around acting shy and cute and play games when giving
you your food and drink which are amusing, embarrassing and, well, cute. The food and drink is
usually vastly overpriced (and there’s an entry fee on top of that) but it was still a cool
experience. Sad to think how many people go there just because there are cute girls who have to act
as if they like you, but fun if you don’t take it too seriously. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was pretty much all we had time for in Akiba. We grabbed a quick bowl of udon before leaving
(traditional food here is incredibly cheap — $5 will get you a filling and tasty meal in most
noodle/curry shops) and then went our separate ways. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trains here are very easy and fast, although that’s something I expected from Japan. However, I
did have a rather disturbing reminder of that efficiency while returning from Akihabara when someone
apparently attempted suicide by throwing themselves under a train on that line (I didn’t gather
whether it was the one I was on or not). There was a brief announcement and a sign saying
“Delayed — passenger injury”, but soon afterwards the train started moving again as if nothing had
happened. It was delayed for under a minute. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A rare clear patch among the crowds&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A rare clear patch among the crowds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the next day exploring Ikebukuro. There isn’t much to say that can’t be explained better in
pictures, so here goes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s not quite so pretty in daylight …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It’s not quite so pretty in daylight …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;$40 for a melon?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;$40 for a melon?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Hmm, this doesn’t look Japanese …&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hmm, this doesn’t look Japanese …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wait, Lumine, Gucci and Gap? Am I really in Japan?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Wait, Lumine, Gucci and Gap? Am I really in Japan?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The first floor of an 8-floor electronics store. Which has a supplementary 6-floor branch across the road. And a 5-floor outlet store two blocks down the road. Heaven!&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The first floor of an 8-floor electronics store. Which has a supplementary 6-floor branch across the road. And a 5-floor outlet store two blocks down the road. Heaven!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;10.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yep, night is when Ikebukuro is truly amazing&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Yep, night is when Ikebukuro is truly amazing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I also moved into my permanent accommodation. It’s 10 minutes (by train) from Ikebukuro.
It’s basically in the geographical centre of the Tokyo urban area. And it feels more like a village
than a city. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Okay, Heiwadai by night isn’t quite so impressive&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Okay, Heiwadai by night isn’t quite so impressive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s really weird to think that I’m still in Tokyo — a feeling I’m sure I’ll expand on in subsequent
posts — but I’m quite glad to be in a quieter place. Ikebukuro is awesome to visit, but I wouldn’t
want to live there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird things &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know that stuff I was saying about convenience stores? Well, every convenience store proudly
advertises the fact that it sells alcohol and cigarettes. Apparently the anti-smoking and
anti-drinking campaigns aren’t as widespread here … &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit is expensive here — even in supermarkets (where the melons are less than $40, you’ll be
pleased to know) you still pay $1 per kiwifruit and $1.50 per apple. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I haven’t yet gathered whether it’s a law or not, but everyone sticks to the left-hand side of
escalators. It’s spooky, especially considering how pushy the Japanese are in crowds. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tale of flights and arrivals</title>
      <link>http://mingard.io/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jono Mingard</dc:creator>
      <category>travel</category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jekyllrb.comblog/2014/03/31/this-is-japan</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Air travel is weird. About 24 hours ago I was sitting in a flying people-box which was hurling me
towards Japan at 600kph. I was trusting my life to two people I’ve never met and will probably never
hear of again. Because the can dropped back to earth safely, I’m now sitting writing this in a hotel
room in Ikebukuro, Tokyo, Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an incredibly well-stocked room which includes a ferociously complicated bathroom (5 different
shower heads and a typically complicated toilet control panel), fridge, kettle, dressing gown,
slippers, clothes brush, toothbrush, razor and (for some reason) a shoehorn. After the rather
spartan airport hotel I was at last night, this feels like the lap of luxury. Well, it would do if
it wasn’t a tiny room with barely space to lay down my suitcase, but I guess that’s what you get
when 10% of the population of Japan are packed into 0.6% of its area (that’s 13 million people in
2000 square kilometers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;So … I guess I just woke up in Tokyo&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;So … I guess I just woke up in Tokyo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The travel itself went quite smoothly — the only hairy moment was at the Gold Coast airport where I
transferred to the flight to Japan. I didn’t realise I would have to go through security again
there, despite having been through at Auckland airport. I also forgot that I was carrying a water
bottle which I bought after going through security at Auckland. After having that confiscated and my
bag searched I was let through so it was only a minor drama, but it was still annoying at the time.
Apparently Australians don’t trust New Zealanders to do security checks …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My last view of Wellington … or at least the cloud above Wellington&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My last view of Wellington … or at least the cloud above Wellington&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always think people don’t talk enough on planes — it’s a good opportunity to meet someone with a
story or two (and who has been forced to sit next to you for several hours). Having said that, I
rarely do start conversations because being antisocial and watching movies is an easy way out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I’m mentioning this is that out of the three flights I’ve been on over the past two days
I’ve had two conversational neighbours and therefore two interesting and useful conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While flying to Auckland I was surprised to find myself sitting next to a 70-year old who had been a
computer programmer in the days of punched cards. I’m fascinated by the history of computing so we
had a fascinating (if you’re not a programmer read: boring) discussion about algorithms, memory and
US elections. In return, since he grew up in a small town in the North Island, I told him about the
current New Zealand education system. He started the conversation by getting a combo meal and
offering me the drink, so I’ve filed that under “conversation starters to use when I’m no longer a
poor student”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way from Auckland to the Gold Coast I was next to a couple who spent the flight in each
others’ arms, but on the flight from the Gold Coast to Narita I was next to two Japanese girls, both
of which were very happy to try and understand my broken Japanese. Aiko, to whom I will be eternally
grateful, ended up showing me to my hotel and taking me around Tokyo. She’d been on exchange in
Sydney so her English was considerably better than my Japanese, and with the help of her
explanations and ‘charenji’ (getting me to ask random strangers about stuff) I’ve gained a little
more confidence in my ability to navigate the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for some weird things — I’ll probably finish off each post in this series with a few things I
found strange or funny. If I haven’t found anything strange or funny, it probably means I’m back
in New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite being a technologically advanced society, the Japanese rarely use credit cards and prefer
to buy things with cash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are convenience stores everywhere — you get a sense of deja vu when you walk past a “Family
Mart” or 7Eleven for the fifth time in as many minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can’t just buy drinks and snacks from vending machines. Coffee, ice cream, burgers and soup
are also readily available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You may notice there aren’t many photos in this post. I didn’t bother taking many at the airports,
but rest assured that actual photos of Tokyo and of me are coming in subsequent articles!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
